（欢快的音乐）
(upbeat music)
- 文本嵌入和语义搜索。
- Text embeddings and semantic search.
在本视频中，我们将探索 Transformer 如何建模
In this video we'll explore how Transformer models
将文本表示为嵌入向量
represent text as embedding vectors
以及如何使用这些向量来查找相似文档
and how these vectors can be used to find similar documents
在语料库中。
in a corpus.
文本嵌入只是一种奇特的说法
Text embeddings are just a fancy way of saying
我们可以将文本表示为数字数组
that we can represent text as an array of numbers
称为矢量。
called a vector.
为了创建这些嵌入，我们通常使用
To create these embeddings we usually use
基于编码器的模型，如 BERT。
an encoder-based model like BERT.
在此示例中，你可以看到我们如何提供三个句子
In this example, you can see how we feed three sentences
到编码器并获得三个向量作为输出。
to the encoder and get three vectors as the output.
读课文，我们可以看到遛狗
Reading the text, we can see that walking the dog
好像跟遛猫最像，
seems to be most similar to walking the cat,
但让我们看看我们是否可以对此进行量化。
but let's see if we can quantify this.
进行比较的技巧
The trick to do the comparison
是计算相似性度量
is to compute a similarity metric
在每对嵌入向量之间。
between each pair of embedding vectors.
这些向量通常存在于一个非常高维的空间中，
These vectors usually live in a very high-dimensional space,
所以相似性度量可以是任何可以衡量的东西
so a similarity metric can be anything that measures
矢量之间的某种距离。
some sort of distance between vectors.
一个非常流行的指标是余弦相似度，
One very popular metric is cosine similarity,
它使用两个向量之间的角度
which uses the angle between two vectors
来衡量他们有多接近。
to measure how close they are.
在这个例子中，我们的嵌入向量存在于 3D 中
In this example, our embedding vectors live in 3D
我们可以看到橙色和灰色向量
and we can see that the orange and Grey vectors
彼此靠近并且具有较小的角度。
are close to each other and have a smaller angle.
现在我们必须处理一个问题
Now one problem we have to deal with
是像 BERT 这样的 Transformer 模型实际上会返回
is that Transformer models like BERT will actually return
每个标记一个嵌入向量。
one embedding vector per token.
例如在句子中，“我带我的狗去散步，”
For example in the sentence, "I took my dog for a walk,"
我们可以期待几个嵌入向量，每个词一个。
we can expect several embedding vectors, one for each word.
例如，在这里我们可以看到模型的输出
For example, here we can see the output of our model
每个句子产生了 9 个嵌入向量，
has produced 9 embedding vectors per sentence,
每个向量有 384 个维度。
and each vector has 384 dimensions.
但我们真正想要的是一个单一的嵌入向量
But what we really want is a single embedding vector
对于每个句子。
for each sentence.
为了解决这个问题，我们可以使用一种称为池化的技术。
To deal with this, we can use a technique called pooling.
最简单的池化方法
The simplest pooling method
就是把令牌嵌入
is to just take the token embedding
特殊的 CLS 令牌。
of the special CLS token.
或者，我们可以对令牌嵌入进行平均
Alternatively, we can average the token embeddings
这就是所谓的均值池，这就是我们在这里所做的。
which is called mean pooling and this is what we do here.
使用均值池是我们唯一需要确保的事情
With mean pooling the only thing we need to make sure
是我们不在平均值中包含填充标记，
is that we don't include the padding tokens in the average,
这就是为什么你可以看到这里使用的注意力掩码。
which is why you can see the attention mask being used here.
这为每个句子提供了一个 384 维向量
This gives us a 384 dimensional vector for each sentence
这正是我们想要的。
which is exactly what we want.
一旦我们有了句子嵌入，
And once we have our sentence embeddings,
我们可以计算余弦相似度
we can compute the cosine similarity
对于每对向量。
for each pair of vectors.
在此示例中，我们使用 scikit-learn 中的函数
In this example we use the function from scikit-learn
你可以看到 “I tok my dog for a walk” 这句话
and you can see that the sentence "I took my dog for a walk"
确实与 “我带我的猫去散步” 有很强的重叠。
has indeed a strong overlap with "I took my cat for a walk".
万岁！我们做到了。
Hooray! We've done it.
我们实际上可以将这个想法更进一步
We can actually take this idea one step further
通过比较问题之间的相似性
by comparing the similarity between a question
和文档语料库。
and a corpus of documents.
例如，假设我们嵌入每个帖子
For example, suppose we embed every post
在 Hugging Face 论坛中。
in the Hugging Face forums.
然后我们可以问一个问题，嵌入它，
We can then ask a question, embed it,
并检查哪些论坛帖子最相似。
and check which forum posts are most similar.
这个过程通常称为语义搜索，
This process is often called semantic search,
因为它允许我们将查询与上下文进行比较。
because it allows us to compare queries with context.
创建语义搜索引擎
To create a semantic search engine
在数据集库中其实很简单。
is actually quite simple in the datasets library.
首先我们需要嵌入所有文档。
First we need to embed all the documents.
在这个例子中，我们取了一个小样本
And in this example, we take a small sample
来自 SQUAD 数据集并应用
from the SQUAD dataset and apply
与以前相同的嵌入逻辑。
the same embedding logic as before.
这为我们提供了一个名为嵌入的新列，
This gives us a new column called embeddings,
它存储每个段落的嵌入。
which stores the embeddings of every passage.
一旦我们有了嵌入，
Once we have our embeddings,
我们需要一种方法来为查询找到最近的邻居。
we need a way to find nearest neighbors for a query.
数据集库提供了一个名为 FAISS 的特殊对象
The datasets library provides a special object called FAISS
这使你可以快速比较嵌入向量。
which allows you to quickly compare embedding vectors.
所以我们添加 FAISS 索引，嵌入一个问题，瞧，
So we add the FAISS index, embed a question and voila,
我们现在找到了 3 篇最相似的文章
we've now found the 3 most similar articles
这可能会存储答案。
which might store the answer.
（欢快的音乐）
(upbeat music)